Hampton L. Carson Papers 1921-1993 Mss.Ms.Coll.83
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV. Works by others, 1949-1987; 1 lin. foot
  - "Measurement of Niche Breadth and Overlap: The Coldwell-Futuyma Model", 1972; Sabath, Michael D. and J. Michael Jones
  - "Genetic Analysis of a Hybrid Zone Between domesticus and musculus Mice ( Mus musculus Complex): Hemoglobin Polymorphisms", 1986; Sage, Richard D., J.B. Whitney III and A.C. Wilson
    -See also Ser.VI, Genetics of Racial Differences (Zoology 415)
  - "Wormy Mice in Hybrid Zone", 1986; Sage, Richard D., Donald Heyneman, Kee-Chong Lim, and Allan C. Wilson
  - "X-Ray Induced Drosophila Mutations Screened by Use of Parthenogenetically-Reproducing Females", 1967; Snyder, Sally Lee H.
  - Genetics Project, 1969; Spector, Elaine B.
  - [Project Plans], Summer 1963; Steiner, Christine
  - "Habitat Choice in Natural Populations of Drosophila", n.d.; Taylor, Charles E.
  - "Density Dependent Selection in Parthenogenetic and Self-Mating Populations", Templeton, Alan Robert
  - "The Evolutionary Biology of Drosophila mercatorum", 1974-1977; Templeton, Alan Robert
  - "The Mechanism of Parthenogenesis and the Inheritance of Light in Drosophila mercatorum", 1969; Templeton, Alan Robert
  - "Parthenogenesis as a Strategy for Studying Genetic Organization", n.d.; Templeton, Alan R. and Charles F. Sing
  - "Detection of Simple Polygenic Segregations in a Natural Population", 1985; Thompson, James N. and C.G. Nicholas Mascie-Taylor
  - Plant Geography (Botany 465) -- Lecture Notes, 1949-1950; Tryon, R.M. Jr.
  - "Ecology of Drosophilid Breeding Sites", n.d.; Villa, Jaime
  - "Frog Embryos: An unusual Feeding Niche", 1975; Villa, Jaime
  - "Mating Preferences and the Direction of Evolution in Drosophila", 1978; Watanabe, Takao K. and Masaoki Kawanishi
  - "Mode of Inheritance and Sexual Behavior in the Parthenogenetic Strains of D. mercatorum", 1968; Wei, Irene Yi-Lien
  - "Topics in Population Genetics: Introduction to the Program", 1983; Weir, Bruce S.
- Series V. Research notes, 1921-1993; 3.5 lin. feet
  Field notes and experimental data, which are usually filed either by species or geographic location. In this series, the genus "Drosophila" is abbreviated "D," when it appears with a species name in a folder title. The bulk of this series concerns Carson's work with D. mercatorum between 1961 and 1985. Also included here are Carson's personal pocket notebooks (1943-1993), which he used for jotting down information ranging from the logistical details of field trips to observations and ideas about his research.
  - Australia -- Drosophila Species, n.d.
  - Bahamas, 2 Folders, 1964-1965, n.d.
    -See also Ser.VII, D. carcinophila -- Bahamas
  - Banana Trap Summaries, 1946-1966
  - Blood Parasites in Common Birds, 1944
  - Caribbean Drosophila -- Notebook
  - Cayman Islands, 1967
  - Christmas Island, 1961
    -See also Extra-oversized
  - Darien, Bogota, 1960
  - D. americana, 4 folders
    - Cytology, 1951-1952, 1970, n.d.
    - Experiment #A1, n.d.
    - Florida, 1962-1967
    - Salivary Glands, 1950s
  - D. bocainensis -- Central America, 1956
  - D. bocainensis- parabocainensis -- Cytology of Hybrid $$, 1951-1953, n.d.
  - D. buzzattii, n.d.
    -See also Ser.VII, D. stalkeri and D. buzzattii
  - D. capricorni and fumipennis Chromosome Variability
  - D. carcinophila
    - D. carcinophila, n.d.
      -See Oversized
    - Montserrat, 1963-1964
    - Infections of Gecarcoidea ruricola, 1965
  - D. carsoni, 1950s
  - Drosophila Ecology, 1948-1949
    - Book 1, 1948-1949; 2 folders
    - Book 2, 1949
  - Drosophila Identification Keys, 1921, 1953-1954, n.d.
  - D. endobranchia, 1965-1966, n.d.
  - D. immigrans, n.d.
  - D. mangabeirai
    - D. mangabeirai, 1950-1960
    - Experiment #K1, 1957-1958
    - Experiment #K2, 1958
  - D. melanogaster
    - Chromosomes, 1955?
    - Experiments W-1 and W-2, 1958
    - M6-A,B,C,D, Strong Selection Experiments #1 and #2, 1959-1961; 2 folders
    - Speciation, 1975
    - Transduction Experiment, n.d.
  - [ D. melanogaster] -- O5 C and D Coadaptation Experiments #1 and #2, 1960-1963; 2 folders
  - D. mercatorum
    - D. mercatorum, 1983-1985
    - Bridge Stocks, 1970-1984
    - Columbia, Peru, and Brazil, 1964-1973
    - Diploidization, 1970-1975; 3 folders
    - Fertility of Sons of Partheogenetic Stocks, 1972-1981
    - Hawaii Wild Strains, 1963-1967
    - Individual Performance in Parthenogenesis Females of RS-3 $, 1962
    - Linkage Groups, 1969-1972
    - Mating Propensity, 1971-1973; 1983-1984; 4 folders
    - Mating Propensity: Effect of O-3-Im on Salvador, 1974-1982; 2 folders
    - Mating Propensity: Variation in S-1 Im, 1982; 3 folders
    - Parthenogenetic Isolates, 1972-1973
    - Polytene Chromosomes, 1966
    - Project Ideas, 1973, 1976
    - Rates of Parthenogenesis, 1973
    - Rates of Parthenogenesis: R-3 Iso Females, n.d.
    - Selection for Parthenogenesis, 1962-1969
    - Selection for Parthenogenesis: Rochester-1 (R-11-Bi), 1961-1963
    - Selection for Parthenogenesis: Rochester x Salavador, 1961-1965
    - Selection for Parthenogenesis: SO and OB Lines, 1966
    - Spermatheca, n.d.
    - Stock Lists, 1975-1981
    - x D. paranensis, 1970-1973
    - XO Males, 1969-1983
    - X-Ray Experiments, 1967-1971
  - D. parthenogenetica, n.d.
  - D. repleta, 1963, n.d.
    -See also Ser.VII, D. repleta -- Puerto Rico
    -See also Ser.VII, D. repleta -- Chromosomes
  - D. stalkeri, 1963
    -See also Ser.VII, D. stalkeri -- Puerto Rico
  - D. sulfurigaster -- Parthenogenesis Test, n.d.
  - Exotic DNA Notes, 1984
  - Galapagos, 1970s
  - Gecarcinus lateralis Kodachromes, n.d.
  - Japan, 1966
  - M5 A and B Coadaptation Experiment, 1959-1962
  - Marshall Islands, 1966
  - Meramec River Project, 1950-1955
    -See also Ser.I, Unidentified, 31 January 1955
  - Mating Capacity in O-3-Im Females, 1971
  - Mycetobia and Schildomyia
  - Notebooks, 4 folders
    - Folder #1, 1953-1960
    - Folder #2, 1962-1964
    - Folder #3, 1965-1969
    - Folder #4, 1977-1993, n.d.
  - Oogenesis In Lonchoptera, n.d.
  - Origin of Parthenogenesis, 1986
  - Pacific and Latin America, 1966
  - Papau New Guinea, 3 folders
    - Papau New Guinea, 1960s-1980s
    - Drosophila Species Groups, 2 folders
      - Folder #1, 1977
      - Folder #2, [1960-1980]
  - Parthenogenesis Experiments, n.d.
  - Puerto Rico Ecology and Drosophila, 1955-1964, n.d.
    -See also Ser. VII, same title
  - Polymorphism in Gecarcinus, 1965
  - Sciara, ca. 1950
  - Sigma Virus Project, 1975-1976
  - Slime Fluxes, 1949-1952
  - Sonoran Desert at Soldier's Trail, 1967
  - Special Techniques and Baits, 1940s-1970s
  - Species Work Sheet, n.d.
  - Sunflower Cecidomyiids, 1945
  - Tyson Valley, 1966
  - Water Hazard Experiments with Drosophila, n.d.
  - West Indies Collecting Areas, 1965-1966
  - Yosemite Region, California and Drosophila Ecology, 1950
- Series VI. Course material, 1943-1986; 2.5 lin. feet
  Lectures that Carson gave for courses at Washington University and the University of Hawaii. Course numbers are given on the folder when a particular number appeared frequently in the course materials. Nine files include materials for a course titled Evolution and Genetics (Zoology/Biology 415-416), which Carson apparently team taught with Harrison Stalker for a certain period of time.
  - British Broadcasting Corporation -- The Open University, n.d.
  - Chromosome Aberations, 1971-1973
  - Cytogenetics Seminars, 1953-1967
  - Cytology (Zoology 426), 3 folders
    - Folders 1-2, [1940s-1970s]; 2 folders
    - Exams, 1943-1964
  - Diploidization, 1973-1974
  - D. mercatorum Fusion Experiment (Genetics 671), 1982
  - Eugenics (Zoology 204), 1951, n.d.
  - Evolution and Genetics (Zoology/Biology 415-416), 9 folders
    - Folders 1-8, [1940s-1970s]; 8 folders
    - Notes on Harrison D. Stalker's Lectures, 1957-1959
  - Evolution Lectures, 1951, 1983-1984, 1987, n.d.
  - Evolution Seminar, 1948
  - Evolutionary Genetics (Genetics 604), 1970-1986; 3 folders
  - Evolutionary Genetics Examinations, 1959-1986
  - Founder Evolution
  - Frequency-Dependent Selection
  - Genetic Variability in Natural Populations, 1970-1986
  - Genetics and Human Affairs (Genetics 625), 1980-1981
  - Genetics Seminar, 1972-1973
  - Geographical Speciation, n.d.
  - Hereditarian Attitudes, 1964
  - Histology (Zoology 425), 1946-1963; 3 folders
  - Introgression, n.d.
  - Isolation, n.d.
  - Meiosis-Syngamy Chiasma Lore, n.d.
  - Microbiological Genetics, n.d.
  - Mobile Genetic Element, 1985
  - Modern Evolutionary Theory (Zoology 202-203), 1954,1960
  - Narcissus Material, 1960-1969
  - Natural History of the Hawaiian Islands (Botany/Zoology 450), 1972
  - Natural Examples of Selection, n.d.
  - Nucleaus and Nucleic Acids (Biology 415-444), 1960-1965, n.d.
  - Parisitology (Zoology 417-418), 1943-1950; 3 folders
  - Parthenogenesis, 1958
  - Polyploidy-Aneuploidy and Evolution
  - Population Genetics (Biology 416) -- Normalizing Selection, 1974, n.d.
    -See also Ser.VI, Evolutionary Genetics (Genetics 604)
  - Principles of Genetics (Genetics 451), 1971-1972
  - Random Drift
  - Qualifying and Comprehensive Examinations, 1974-1975
  - Selected Topics in Genetics in Relation to Cancer, 1971-1972
  - Summer Institute of Zoology for College Teachers -- Lectures in Evolutionary Genetics, 1956
  - Sympatric Speciation, n.d.
  - Techniques in Genetics (Genetics 671), 1965-1984; 4 folders
  - University of California. Perspectives in Genetics Seminar (Genetics 199), n.d.
    -See Ser.III, "The Genetics of Marginal vs. Central Populations" -- Lecture
  - Zoology 444, 1964, 1969
    Includes notes on Tradescantia, Dandelions, Drosophila Projects, and Selection Experiment
- Series VII. Photographs, 1948-1985; 0.5 lin. feet
  Prints, slides, and negatives. The photographs are primarily related to Carson's research, and they appear in files with the same title to a corresponding file in Series I, II, or V with which they are cross-referenced.
  - [ADH Gene], 1983
  - Ahuja, Yog, 1993
  - Carson, Hampton L. -- Portraits, 1960-1970?
  - Carson, Hampton Lawrence -- Visa, 1978
  - Carson, Meredith S. -- Visa, 1978
  - "Change in a Secondary Character as Evidence of Incipient Speciation in Drosophila silvestris", 1979
  - Christmas Island, 1961
  - "Chromosomal Sequences and Interisland Colonizations in Hawaiian Drosophila", 1983
  - "Chromosomal Tracing of Evolution in a Phylad of Species Related to Drosophila hawaiiensis", 1975
  - "Drosophilidae Associated with Flowers in Papau New Guinea. I. Colocasia esculenta", 1979
  - D. bocainsensis-parabocainsensis Cytology of Hybrid $$, 1951, 1953
  - D. carcinophila
    - D. carcinophila, n.d.
    - Bahamas, 1965
    - Montserrat, 1963-1964
  - Drosophila Ecology
    - Book 1, 1948-1949
    - Book 2, 1949
  - D. endobranchia, 1965
  - D. immigrans, n.d.
  - D. mangabeirai, ca. 1960
  - D. melanogaster -- Chromosomes, 1955?
  - D. mercatorum
    - Mosaics, 1973
    - Polytene Chromosomes, 1966
    - Spermatheca, n.d.
    - x D. paranaensis, 1970-1973
  - D. repleta
    - Chromosomes, n.d.
    - Puerto Rico, n.d.
  - D. stalkeri
    - Montserrat and Puerto Rico
    - and D. buzzatti
  - "The Ecology of Drosophila Breeding Sites", 1970-1971
  - Evolutionary Processes and Theory -- Workshop, 1985
  - Genetic Microdifferentiation in Human and Other Animal Populations Symposium, 1983
  - Hsu, T.C. -- Human Spleen Cell, 18 April 1952
  - Ikeda, Hiroshi -- BCR5 (Slow Mating Strain), 19 August 1975
  - Japan, 1966
    From H. Ikeda
  - "Metaphase Karyotype Identity in Four Homosequential Drosophila Species From Hawaii", 1985
  - Papau New Guinea, 1977
  - Polymorphism in Gecarcinus, 1965
  - Puerto Rico Ecology and Drosophila
  - Sunflower Cecidomyiids, 1945
  - Techniques in Genetics (Genetics 671) #2, 1965-1984
  - "Three Flies and Three Islands: Parallel Evolution in Drosophila", 1974
  - 1978, United States-Japan Cooperative Science Program.
  - Universita Di Pavia -- Symposium on Genetics of Population Structure, 1953